Guide to the Brockett collection, 1773-1890.
Brockett collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Brockett collection, 1773-1890
381
Frank S., Brockett
.3 cubic ft.; 4 v.
Deeds, bonds, accounts, lists, scrapbooks, letters, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Deeds, bonds, accounts, lists, scrapbooks, and letters pertaining to the Irvine family and Albany, Rensselaer and Washington Counties, New York. Deeds from Alexander and Cadwallader Colden. Also, papers pertaining to the Lourie family, of Washington County, including lists from "The Old Town" book (1773-1816) including slave owners, school districts, fire wardens, and town meetings of Albany County. Scrapbooks of John S. Crocker, Warden of the United States Jail in Washington, D. C., relating to President Garfield, Guiteau, the Jail, Washington, D. C. and other topics; letters from Crocker to his wife from Albany, Rikers Island, Libby Prison, Salisbury Prison, and from his stations with McClellan's and Burnside's armies, describing in detail the problems of his commands, his capture, a number of campaigns, and the Battle of Fredericksburg.
CHRONOLOGY--GENERAL JOHN S. CROCKER
1820, March 4 Born, son of Col. Francis Crocker and Anna Woodworth, of Cambridge, N.Y. Both of Revolutionary War ancestry. Col. Crocker a Mayflower descendent.
1834 Gen. Crocker began his military career by organizing a company of schoolboys, of which he was elected Captain - so well drilled and disciplined the company were the pride of the village.
1837 Taught school at Ashgrove, suburb of Cambridge.
1840 Commissioned First Lieutenant of artillery, attached to 14th Regiment of N.Y. State Militia by Gov. Seward. During the next twenty years rose through the successive grades of Captain, Lieutenant Colonel, Colonel, and General in the State Militia, thus forming State-wide acquaintance among military men and officials.
1843 Was married on June 13 to Harriette Sipperly of Melrose, N.Y. They had three sons, John S., Jr., Irving M., and Willis F. Crocker.
1846 Was admitted to the New York State Bar, having studied law in the office of Judge Howe of Cambridge and Albany Law School.
1855 Joined the "Know Nothings" and appoint Deputy for the first assembly district of Washington County.
1855 Elected member of the New York State Assembly.
1860 Organized Cambridge Valley Lodge #481, F&AM (chartered June 12) and was elected J.W. of the Lodge. (When living in Washington, D.C. after close of Civil War, advanced to the 33rd and highest Degree in Masonry and was a brother Lodge member of President James A. Garfield.)
1861 Governor Morgan authorized him to raise and drill a Regiment of Volunteer Infantry. Quickly mustered 1030 outstanding men, mostly from Washington, Warren, Essex, and Rensselaer Counties. This Regiment was numbered the 93rd N.Y.V. and were christened "Morgan Rifles" in honor of Governor Morgan.
1862, January 30 Col. Crocker and his Regimental officers were commissioned and shortly thereafter left for Washington and became attached to the Army of the Potomac under General Geo. B. McClellan, and during 1862-1863 served as Headquarters Guard of this Army, under McClellan, Burnside, Hooker, and Meade, participating in the Peninsular Campaign, Antietem, Fredericksburg, and Gettysburg.
1864 Expiration, in January, of enlistment; furloughed, and re-enlisted as a Veteran Regiment, the first of this class of the Army of the Potomac, and then took the field and fought under Gen. Grant up to the time of Lee's surrender at Appomattox.
1864 At the Battle of the Wilderness, May 5, the 93rd N.Y.V. were cited by General Birney for outstanding gallantry, and Colonel Crocker was made a Brigadier General in the field on the death of General Hayes. In this battle, General Crocker had four horses killed under him and himself was severely wounded.
1865, May 23 The remnants of this renowned Regiment participated in the Grand Review on Pennsylvania Avenue at Washington, D.C.
1865-1869 Was a practicing lawyer in Washington.
1869 Was appointed by President U.S. Grant Warden of the United States Jail at Washington, which he held until his death in 1890. During his tenure of office, he officiated at the hanging of Charles J. Guiteau, the assassinator of President James A. Garfield. Also during this period he was very active in politics in the city, being President of the Board of Aldermen and Acting Mayor. He had very active participation in the filling in of the Canal and levelling of Washington's streets, directed by the hard-bitten and resolute "Boss" Shepard.
1890 Died.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Deeds, bonds, accounts, lists, scrapbooks, and letters pertaining to the Irvine family and Albany, Rensselaer and Washington Counties, New York. Deeds from Alexander and Cadwallader Colden. Also, papers pertaining to the Lourie family, of Washington County, including lists from "The Old Town" book (1773-1816) including slave owners, school districts, fire wardens, and town meetings of Albany County. Scrapbooks of John S. Crocker, Warden of the United States Jail in Washington, D. C., relating to President Garfield, Guiteau, the Jail, Washington, D. C. and other topics; letters from Crocker to his wife from Albany, Rikers Island, Libby Prison, Salisbury Prison, and from his stations with McClellan's and Burnside's armies, describing in detail the problems of his commands, his capture, a number of campaigns, and the Battle of Fredericksburg.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Brockett, Frank S.,; Burnside, Ambrose Everett, 1824-1881.; Colden, Alexander.; Colden, Cadwallader R., 1774-1839.; Crocker, John S., d. 1890.; Garfield, James A., (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Guiteau, Charles Julius, 1841-1882.; Irvine family.; Lourie family.; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1885.; Libby Prison.; Salisbury Prison (N.C.)
Subjects:
Prisons--Washington (D.C.); Slavery--New York (State)--Albany County.; Education--New York (State).; Family--New York (State)--Albany County.; Fredericksburg, Battle of, Fredericksburg, Va., 1862.
Places:
Albany County (N.Y.)--History, Local.; Rensselaer County (N.Y.)--History, Local.; Washington County (N.Y.)--History, Local.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Albany County (N.Y.)--Politics and government.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Deeds.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Indenture, From William Bradshaw to George Duncan, Albany County, December 17, 1778 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From John Johnston to George Duncan and John Moor, Albany County, February 11, 1784 (Box 1)
- Deed, From William Edgar to James Irvine, Albany County, December 15, 1786 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Alexander Golden to James Irvine and James Blake, Albany County, February 15, 1794 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Thompson to William Mushet, Washington County, September 7, 1794 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Jonathan French to Alexander Lourey, Washington County, September 15, 1796 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Blake to James Irvine, Washington County, April 15, 1797 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Black and James Irvine to H.N. Colden, Washington County, August 28, 1798 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From William Edgar and Ann, his wife, to James Irvine, Washington County, 1799 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From William Mushet and Mary, his wife, to Alexander Lourie, Washington County, November 2, 1799 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Irvine to Robert Irvine, Washington County, September 16, 1800 (Box 1)
- Bond, from James Irvine to William McAuley, Washington County, September 16, 1800 (Box 1)
- Bond for a Deed, From Iudah Weeks to James Devanny, Bennington County and Washington County, November 21, 1801 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Irvine and Mary, his wife, to William McAuley, Washington County, May 4, 1804 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Cadwallader Colden to James Irvine, Rennselaer County, and Washington County, January 31, 1804 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From C.R. Colden to James Irvine and Benjamin Fuitin, Washington County, July 9, 1807 (Box 1)
- Agreement, Between John Miller and Mumphard Kinyon and Israel Whipple, Washington County, May 31, 1809 (Box 1)
- Bond, From James Irvine and George Miller to John Robinson, Washington County, February 13, 1811 (Box 1)
- Agreement, Between John Welsh and George Lourie, Washington County, February 7, 1812 (Box 1)
- Agreement, Between Samuel McDonal and George Lourie and Henry McAuley, Washington County, April 3, 1813 (Box 1)
- Long Bill of Goods, From George Lourie to William Stevenson and Company, 1813 (Box 1)
- Agreement, Between John Mushet and George Lourie, Washington County, January 6, 1812 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From George Lourie to Alexander Lourie, Washington County, February 22, 1812 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Alexander Lourie to George Lourie, Washington County, February 22, 1812 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From James Irvine to George Lourie, Washington County, March 11, 1816 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Reuben J. Blanchard to George Lourie, Washington County, November 15, 1819 (Box 1)
- Oath before the justice of the peace, James Irvine by Chancy Scovil in favor of William Stevenson for one hundred dollars and ninety-four cents, Washington County, April 30, 1819 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From Robert McAuley, Washington County, to Patty Lee, Saratoga County, December 29, 1820 (Box 1)
- Inventory of the goods, chattels, and credits of James Irvine, deceased, Washington County, December 14, 1820. (Box 1)
- Bill of Sale, From Samuel McDonal to George Lourie and James Hay, Washington County, December 6, 1821 (Box 1)
- Agreement, Between Mary Irvine, Jackson and Robert Pearson, Whitecreek, March 14, 1823 (Box 1)
- Letter, From Margaret (Lourie) Armstrong, Lisbon to Mr. Alexander Lourie on the possibilities of acquiring fifty acres of land and church affairs, June 11, 1827 (Box 1)
- Letter, From John Robertson to George Lourie, Jackson, concerning a mortgage, February 5, 1830 (Box 1)
- Statement or Certificate by Charles F. Ingles that Mr. McDonal would pay the one dollar fee for David Johnson in the suit David Johnson vs. Henry McAuley, March 10, 1839 (Box 1)
- Bond, From Samuel McDonal to George Lourie and A.B. McDonal, Washington County, April 1, 1837 (Box 1)
- Application for Fire Insurance, George Lourie, Washington County, 1837 (Box 1)
- Fire Insurance Policy for fifteen hundred and two dollars, George Lourie, Washington County, May 17, 1840 (Box 1)
- Declaration of Trust by George Lourie and James Hay, concerning a bond and mortgage made in their trust by Mary McDonal for her Children, Alexander and Peter McDonal, Washington County, August 15, 1838 (Box 1)
- Road Warrant to George Lourie, overseer to take command the persons whose names are contained in a list, Washington County, District No. 19, April 20, 1838 (Box 1)
- In Account with George; William S. Warner, merchant, Cambridge, March 29, 1847 (Box 1)
- Certificate of life members in American Tract Society to George Lourie from Alexander Bullions Congugation, Cambridge, New York, September 17, 1853 (Box 1)
- Fire Insurance Policy No. 646 for thirty-one hundred and thirty dollars to Thomas B. Lourie, Jackson, New York, December 4, 1882 (Box 1)
- Indenture, From George Duncan to John Mushet and William Mushet, Albany County, March 30, 1886. (Box 1)
- Agreement Between George Lourie and Joe P. Parly, Cambridge, Undated (Box 1)
- List of names, goods and prices, no date. (Box 1)
- Law dealing with marrying members of the Church, no date. (Box 1)
- "Morgan's Men" - Release, October 6. From the October issue of the Recorder: Bulletin of the American Irish Historical Society. (Box 1)
  This article is topical in relation to the ceremonies connected with the 150th anniversary of the Battle of Saratoga, at the Battlefield, Saturday, October 8, 1927 - Morgan's Riflemen at the Battle of Saratoga, by Michael J. O'Brian, Histographer, American Irish Historical Society.
- Lists taken from "The Old Town" book, 1773-1816.
  - Slave Owners in Town of Cambridge. (Box 1)
  - School districts, Cambridge town. (Box 1)
  - Goods sold at Anson Ingrahams Store, Center Cambridge -, 1830-1840 (Box 1)
  - Firemen (five wardens) from the old Cambridge book 1st meeting of Cambridge District. (Box 1)
  - Town Meetings of Cambridge "District," Albany County, Province of New York. (Box 1)
  - Town Meetings of Cambridge "Township," Washington County, State of New York and place and date where held. (Box 1)
  - Commissioners of Roads, Cambridge, 1781 to 1816 (Box 1)
    From the old Cambridge book - dates are when certain members laid out specified Roads.
  - Cambridge - Roads. (Box 1)
  - White Creek - Center White Creek, or "Waite's Corners." (Box 1)
- Rev. J.R. Fisher - historical address (data by Mr. Albert Whiteside), September 12, 1900 (Box 1)
  The centennial of Whiteside.
- Letters (typewritten), December 19, 1861 to May 3, 1864 (Box 1)
  139 items. From John S. Crocker, Col. 93rd N.Y. Vols., Brig. General, Major General U.S., to his wife. Civil War
- Scrap Book, Undated (Volume 1)
  General John S. Crocker, Warden, United States Jail, Washington, D.C. Clippings of poetry, stories, and images taken from various newspapers. Includes a few articles about events involving General Crocker.
- Scrap Book, 1882 to 1889 (Volume 3)
  General John S. Crocker, Warden, United States Jail, Washington, D.C. News clippings and photographs relating to the assassination of President Garfield and the capture and trial of Charles Guiteau, convicted of the assassination. Also material relating to Crocker's appointment of warden and other national events. Maps belonging to Crocker from his time in the Civil War.
- Scrap Book, 1880-1882 (Volume 4)
  General John S. Crocker, Warden, United States Jail, Washington, D.C. News clippings relating to the assassination of President Garfield and the trial and execution of Charles Guiteau, convicted of the assassination. Also material relating to the execution of James Madison Wyatt Stone, convicted of killing his wife.
- George Lourie's Account Book, Cambridge, 1810 (Volume 2)